Silicon Valley is obsessed with disruption,
انتشرت الاضطرابات بوادى السيليكون،
but these days, the biggest disruptor didn't come out of Silicon Valley.
ولكن هذه الأيام، الاضطراب الكبير لم يصدر من وادى السيليكون.
It came out of steel towns in Ohio,
بل صدر من مدن صناعة الصلب في (أوهايو)،
rural communities in Pennsylvania,
والمجتمعات الريفية في (بنسيلفانيا)،
the Panhandle in Florida.
والمتسولين في (فلوريدا).
And this last US presidential election
تسببت الانتخابات الرئاسية الأخيرة
was the mother of all disruptions.
في كل هذه الاضطرابات.
Once again, politics is personal.
مرة أخرى، السياسية أمر شخصي.
Millions of Americans became activists overnight,
أصبح الملايين من الأمريكيين نشطاء بين عشية وضحاها،
pouring into the streets in record numbers
يتدفقون إلى الشوارع بأرقام قياسية
in record time.
في زمن قياسي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The election has done to family holiday dinners
ما فعلته الانتخابات بالعشاء العائلي في الإجازات
what Uber has done to New York City's taxi system.
هو نفس ما فعلته (أوبر) بنظام سيارات الأجرة في (نيويورك).
Couples have broken up and marriages disrupted.
انفصل الأزواج واضطربت الزيجات.
And the election is doing to my private life
وقد فعلت الانتخابات بحياتي الشخصية
what Amazon is doing to shopping malls.
ما فعلته (أمازون) بمراكز التسوق.
These days, the ACLU is on the front lines 24/7,
حاليًا الاتحاد الأمريكي للحريات المدنية في خط المواجهة 24 ساعة طوال أيام الأسبوع،
and even if I manage to sneak away for a couple of miles on the treadmill,
وبالرغم من إمكانية الهروب بضع أميال على آلة الركض الرياضية،
any cardio benefit I get is instantly obliterated
إلا أن أي فائدة صحية للقلب تذهب هباءً على الفور
when I read another presidential tweet on the headline scroll.
عندما أقرأ التغريدات الرئاسية الجديدة.
Even my secret pleasure
حتي سعادتي السرية
of studying the Italian painters
في دراسة الرسامين الإيطاليين
have been infected by politics.
قد أصيبت بالسياسية أيضًا.
Now, I study, even stalk, the old masters.
والآن أنا أدرس أو بالأحرى أطارد الفنانين القدامى.
This is my desk,
هذه طاولتي،
with a postcard exhibition
بها معرض لبطاقات بريدية
of some famous and obscure paintings
لبعض الرسومات المشهورة والغامضة
mostly from the Italian Renaissance.
ينتمي معظمها إلى عصر النهضة الإيطالي.
Now, art used to provide me with a necessary break
كان الفن يمدني بالاستراحة الضرورية
from the hurly-burly of politics
من هرج ومرج السياسة
in my daily work at the ACLU,
في عملي اليومي في الاتحاد الأمريكي للحريات المدنية،
but not anymore.
ولكن لم يعد الأمر كذلك.
I was at the Women's March in San Francisco
حضرت المسيرة النسائية في (سان فرانسسيكو)
the day after inauguration,
في اليوم التالي للانتخابات،
and the crowd was chanting, "This is what democracy looks like."
وكان الجميع يردد "هكذا تبدو الديمقراطية."
And there I was holding my sign and my umbrella in the rain,
بينما أقف هناك حاملًا لافتتي ومظلتي تحت الأمطار،
and I flashed on an old painting
لمعت في ذهني صورة لوحة قديمة
that first captivated me many years ago.
والتي قد أسرتني لأعوام منذ أن رأيتها أول مرة.
I struggled to remember the different pieces
كافحت لأتذكر القطع المختلفة
of an actual painting
للوحة واقعية
of good and bad government.
للحكومات الصالحة والفاسدة.
It was almost like the old master was taunting me.
وكأن فنان اللوحة القديمة يستهزئ بي:
You want to know what democracy looks like?
"هل تريد أن تعلم كيف تبدو الديمقراطية؟
Go back and look at my frescoes.
ارجع وانظر إلى لوحاتي الجصية."
And so I did.
وقد فعلت.
In 1339, Ambrogio Lorenzetti finished a monumental commission
انتهى (امبروجيو لورنزيتي) عام 1339 من عمل بارز
in the governing council chamber of Siena's Palazzo Pubblico.
في قاعة المجلس الحاكم في قصر (بلاتسو بابليكو) في (سيينا).
It's a painting that speaks to us, even screams to us, today.
وهي لوحة تتحدث إلينا أو بالأحرى تصرخ في وجوهنا اليوم.
"Art is a lie that makes us realize truth,"
"الفن هو الكذبة التي تجعلنا ندرك الواقع"
Pablo Picasso once said.
كما قال (بابلو بيكاسو).
And as we search for the truth about government,
وعندما نبحث عن حقيقة الحكومة،
we should keep Ambrogio's work,
ينبغي علينا أن ننظر لأعمال (امبروجيو)
not a lie but an allegory, in our collective mind's eye.
ليس وكأنها كذبة ولكن كأنها رمز في عقلنا الجماعى.
During Lorenzetti's time,
في زمن (لورنزيتي)،
the political legitimacy of Italian city-states
لم تقف الشرعية السياسية للمدن الإيطالية
was often on very shaky ground.
على أرض صلبة.
Siena was a republic,
كانت (سيينا) جمهورية،
but there had been enormous unrest
ولكن كانت تعاني من عدم استقرار كبير
in the two decades leading up to the commission.
خلال عقدين من الزمن انتهت إلى المفوضية.
Siena's political leaders, who would literally govern
زعماء (سيينا) السياسيين الذين كانوا يحكمون بالفعل
under the eyes of these allegorical figures,
تحت مراقبة هذه النماذج الرمزية،
were Lorenzetti's intended audience.
هم جمهور (لورنزيتي) المقصود.
He was cataloging the obligations
كان يصنف التزامات الحاكم للمحكومين.
Now, you can spend years studying these frescoes.
يمكنك أن تمضي أعوامًا في دراسة هذه الأعمال الجصية.
Some scholars have.
قد فعل ذلك بعض العلماء.
I'm hardly an art historian,
أنا بالكاد مؤرخ فني،
but I am passionate about art,
ولكني مولع بالفن،
and a work this massive can overwhelm me.
ويستطيع عمل كبير مثل هذا أن يحوز اهتمامي.
So first, I focus on the big stuff.
في البداية، أركز على الأمور الكبيرة.
This is the allegory of good government.
هذا رمز للحكومة الصالحة.
The majestic figure here in the middle
النموذج المهيب هنا في الوسط
is dressed in Siena's colors
يرتدي ألوان (سيينا)
and he personifies the republic itself.
ويجسد الجمهورية نفسها.
Lorenzetti labels him "Commune,"
يطلق (لورنزيتي) عليه (عامة الشعب)،
and he's basically telling the Sienese
وهو يخبر الشعب السييني
that they, and not a king or a tyrant, must rule themselves.
أنه يجب عليهم حكم أنفسهم وأن لا يدعوا الأمر لملك أو طاغية.
Now, surrounding Commune are his advisors.
وهنا يحيط المستشارون بـ(عامة الشعب).
Justice is enthroned.
وتم تتويج العدالة.
She's looking up at the figure of wisdom,
هي تنظر إلى رمز الحكمة،
who actually supports her scales of justice.
والتي تحمل ميزان العدالة.
Concord, or Harmony,
الوفاق أو التناغم،
holds a string that comes off the scales of justice
يحمل حبلًا ينبعث من ميزان العدالة
that binds her to the citizens,
ويربطها بالمواطنين،
making them all compatriots in the republic.
ويجعلهم جميعًا رفقاء في الجمهورية.
And finally we see Peace.
لنرى السلام في النهاية.
She looks chilled out,
تبدو هادئة الأعصاب،
like she's listening to Bob Marley.
كأنها تستمع إلى (بوب مارلي).
When good government rules,
عندما تتولى الحكومة الصالحة الحكم،
Peace doesn't break a sweat.
يتحقق السلام دون أي جهد.
Now, these are big images and big ideas,
والآن تلك صور كبيرة وأفكار كبيرة،
but I really love the small stuff.
ولكني حقًا أحب الأمور الصغيرة.
Along another wall,
في لوحة أخرى،
Lorenzetti illustrates the effects of good government
يوضح (لورنزيتي) تأثير الحكومة الصالحة
on the real and everyday lives of ordinary people
على الحياة اليومية والحقيقية للأشخاص العاديين
with a series of delicious little details.
في سلسلة من التفاصيل الصغيرة المبهجة.
In the countryside, the hills are landscaped and farmed.
في الريف، يتم تنسيق المساحات الخضراء وحرثها.
Crops are being sown, hoed, reaped, milled, plowed,
يتم زرع الأرض وجرفها وجني ثمارها وطحنها وحرثها،
all in one picture.
كل ذلك في صورة واحدة.
Crops and livestock are being brought to market.
تُجلب المحاصيل والماشية إلى السوق.
In the city, builders raise a tower.
وفي المدينة، يبني البناؤون بُرجًا.
People attend a law lecture, a TED Talk of the 14th century.
يحضر الناس محاضرة عن القانون، محادثة TED في القرن الـ14.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Schoolchildren play.
يلهو طلاب المدارس.
Tradesmen thrive.
يزدهر التجار.
Dancers larger than life dance with joy.
يرقص الراقصون اللامعون ببهجة.
And watching over the republic is the winged figure Security,
ويراقب الجمهورية شخصية رمزية مجنحة تمثل الأمن،
whose banner reads,
وشعاره يقول،
"Everyone shall go forth freely without fear."
"يستطيع الجميع التحرك بحرية دون خوف".
Now, what's amazing about these images from 800 years ago
المدهش في صور عمرها 800 عام
is that they're familiar to us today.
أنها تبدو مألوفة لدينا اليوم.
We see what democracy looks like.
نحن نرى كيف تبدو الديمقراطية.
We experience the effects of good government in our lives,
نرى تأثير الحكومة الصالحة في حياتنا،
just as Lorenzetti did in his life.
مثلما فعل (لورنزيتي) في حياته.
But it is the allegory of bad government
ولكن رمز الحكومة الفاسدة
that has been haunting me since November 9.
هو ما يجول في خاطري منذ 9 نوفمبر.
It's badly damaged,
لقد أُلحق بها ضررًا كبيرًا،
but it reads like today's newspapers.
ولكنها تبدو كصحف أخبار اليوم.
And ruling over bad government is not the Commune
والذي يتحكم في الحكومة الفاسدة ليس عامة الشعب
but the Tyrant.
بل الطاغية.
He has horns, tusks, crossed eyes,
لديه قرون وناب وأحول العينين،
braided hair.
مُضفر الشعر.
He obviously spends a lot of time on that hair.
من الواضح أنه أمضى وقتًا طويلاً في تصفيفه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Justice now lies helpless at his feet,
العدالة الآن تقبع عاجزة تحت قدميه،
shackled.
مُقيدة.
Her scales have been severed.
تم تدمير ميزانها.
Justice is the key antagonist to the Tyrant,
العدالة هي العدو الرئيسي للطاغية،
and she's been taken out.
وها قد تم طردها.
Now, surrounding the Tyrant,
والآن ما يحيط الطاغية،
Lorenzetti illustrates the vices that animate bad government.
كما يوضح (لورنزيتي) الرذائل التي تدعم الحكومة الفاسدة.
Avarice is the old woman clutching the strongbox
الجشع إمرأة عجوزة تتشبث بالخزنة
and a fisherman's hook
وخطاف الصيد
to pull in her fortune.
لتقتلع ثروتها.
Vainglory carries a mirror,
الخيلاء تحمل مرآة.
and Lorenzetti warns us against narcissistic leaders
يحذرنا (لورنزيتي) من القائد النرجسي
who are guided by their own ego and vanity.
الذي يقوده غروره وتكٌبره.
On the Tyrant's right is Cruelty.
عن يمين الطاغية توجد القسوة.
Treason, half lamb, half scorpion,
والخيانة - نصف حمل ونصف عقرب.
lulls us into a false sense of security
يعطينا شعوراً مُضللاً بالأمان
and then poisons a republic.
وبعد ذلك تُسمم الجمهورية.
Fraud, with the flighty wings of a bat.
الاحتيال لديه أجنحة الخُفاش الطائشة.
On the Tyrant's left, you see Division.
وعن شمال الطاغية، ترى الانقسام.
She's dressed in Siena's colors.
إنها ترتدي ألوان (سيينا).
"Si" and "No" are painted on her body.
ومطبوع على جسدها (نعم) و(لا).
She uses a carpenter's saw to chop her body in half.
تستخدم مِنشار النجار لشق جسدها نصفين.
And Fury wields the weapons of the mob,
ويستخدم الغضب سلاح الغوغاء ببراعة:
the stone and knife.
الحجارة والسكين.
In the remainder of the fresco, Lorenzetti shows us
وفي بقية اللوحة يوضح لنا (لورنزيتي)
the inevitable effects of bad government.
النتيجة الحتمية للحكومة الفاسدة.
The civic ideals celebrated elsewhere in this room have failed us,
خذلتنا أي مثالية مدنية تم تمجيدها في هذه القاعة،
and we see it.
ونحن نرى ذلك.
The once beautiful city has fallen to pieces,
المدينة التي كانت جميلة سابقًا قد انهارت،
the countryside barren,
وأُجدب الريف،
the farms abandoned.
وهُجرت المزارع.
Many are in flames.
واشتعلت كثير من البقاع.
And in the sky above is not the winged figure Security,
ولا يوجد في الأعلى رمز الأمانة المجنحة،
but that of Fear, whose banner reads:
و لكن رمز للخوف، وشعاره:
"None shall pass along this road
"لا أحد يمر من هذا الطريق
without fear of death."
دون أن يخاف من الموت."
Now, the final image, the most important one, really,
والآن الصورة النهائية وهي الأهم
is one that Lorenzetti did not paint.
والتي لم يرسمها (لورنزيتي)،
It is of the viewer.
بل هي تعود للمشاهد.
Today, the audience for Lorenzetti's frescoes
اليوم جمهور لوحات (لورنزيتي)
is not the governing but the governed,
ليسوا الحكام بل المحكومين،
the individual who stands in front of his allegories
اللذين يقفون أمام تلك الرموز
and walks away with insight,
ثم يرحلون ببصيرة،
who heeds a call to action.
والذين يدْعون إلى اتخاذ إجراء.
Lorenzetti warns us that we must recognize the shadows
ينبهنا (لورنزيتي) إلى ضرورة إدراك أشباح
of Avarice, Fraud, Division, even Tyranny
الجشع والاحتيال والانقسام والطغيان
when they float across our political landscape,
المستشرية في مشهدنا السياسي،
especially when those shadows are cast
وبالتحديد إذا قام بدور الأشباح
by political leaders loudly claiming to be the voice of good government
قادة سياسيين يزعمون بصخب أنهم يمثلون صوت الحكومة الصالحة
and promising to make America great again.
ويعدون بأنهم سيجعلون ( أمريكا) عظيمة مرة أخرى.
And we must act.
علينا اتخاذ موقف.
Democracy must not be a spectator sport.
لا ينبغي أن تكون الديمقراطية مباراة للمشاهدة.
The right to protest, the right to assemble freely,
حق التظاهر وحق التجمهر بحرية،
the right to petition one's government,
وحق تقديم عريضة إلى حكومتك،
these are not just rights.
هي ليست مجرد حقوق
In the face of Avarice, Fraud and Division,
في مواجهة الجشع والاحتيال والانقسام
these are obligations.
هي التزامات.
We have to disrupt --
علينا إن نُحدث اضطرابًا --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We have to disrupt our lives
علينا أن نُحدث اضطرابًا في حياتنا
so that we can disrupt
كي نستطيع أن نُربك
the amoral accretion of power
النمو المتزايد غير الأخلاقي للسلطة
by those who would betray our values.
لمن يقوم بخيانة قيمنا.
We and we the people
ونحن "الشعب"
must raise justice up
علينا النهوض بالعدالة
and must bring peace to our nation
وتحقيق السلام لأمتنا
and must come together in concord,
ونكون على وفاق،
and we have a choice.
ولدينا الخيار،
We could either paint ourselves
إما أن نرسم أنفسنا
into the worst nightmare of Lorenzetti's bad government,
في كابوس حكومة (لورنزيتي) الفاسدة،
or we can stay in the streets,
أو أن نبقى في الطرقات،
disruptive, messy, loud.
ثائرين وفوضويين وصاخبين.
That is what democracy looks like.
هكذا تبدو الديمقراطية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: First of all, wow.
كريس أندرسون: أولا: هذا رائع.
Obviously, many people passionately --
بالتأكيد العديد من الناس ---
you spoke to many people passionately here.
لقد تحدثت بحماسة لعديد من المشاهدين هنا.
I'm sure there are other people here
ولكن من المؤكد وجود آخرين هنا
who'd say, look, Trump was elected by 63 million people.
سيقولون أنه تم انتخاب ترامب منِ قِبل 63 مليون شخص.
He's far from perfect,
وهو أبعد ما يكون عن المثالية
but he's trying to do what he was elected to do.
ولكنه يحاول أن يقوم بدوره الذي أُنتخب من أجله.
Shouldn't you give him a chance?
ألا يجب أن نعطيه فرصة؟
Anthony Romero: I think we have to recognize
أنتوني روميرو: أعتقد أنه علينا أن ندرك
the legitimacy of him as president
شرعيته كرئيس
versus the legitimacy of his policies.
في مقابل شرعية سياسته.
And when so many of the policies are contrary to fundamental values,
وعندما يكون هناك العديد من السياسات المخالفة للقيم الأساسية،
that we're all equal under the law,
أن جميعنا متساوون أمام القانون،
that we're not judged by the color of our skin or the religion we worship,
ولا يتم الحكم علينا بلون بشرتنا أو بديننا الذي نعتنق،
we have to contest those values
علينا أن نحارب تلك القيم
even as we recognize and honor the fact
حتى وإن كنا ندرك ونقدر حقيقة
that our democracy rendered us a president who is championing those values.
أن ديمقراطيتنا قدمت لنا رئيسًا يدافع عن تلك القيم.
CA: And the ACLU isn't just this force on the left, right?
الاتحاد الأمريكي للحريات المدنية ليس مجرد قوة يسارية، أليس كذلك؟
You're making other arguments as well.
لديك جدالات أخرى أيضًا.
AR: Well, you know,
بالطبع
very often we piss everyone off at one point.
كثيرًا ما نثير غضب الجميع في امر ما.
That's what we do.
وهذا هو عملنا.
And we recently were taking stands
فقد أخذنا مؤخرًا موقفًا
for why Ann Coulter needs to be able to speak at Berkeley,
لتوضيح سبب حاجة آن كولتر لإلقاء كلمة في بيركلي.
and why Milo has free speech rights.
ولماذا ميلو لدية حق حرية التعبير.
And we even wrote a blog
وكتبنا مدونة أيضًا
that almost burnt the house down among some of our members,
والتي كادت أن تضرم النار بين بعض أعضائنا.
unfortunately, when we talked about the fact
للأسف، عندما تحدثنا عن حقيقة
that even Donald Trump has free speech rights as president,
حتّى دونالد ترامب لديه حقوق حرية التعبير كرئيس،
and an effort to hold him accountable
وجهدًا لجعله يتحمل مسئولية
for incitement of violence at his marches or his rallies
التحريض على العنف في مسيراته وتجمعاته
is unconstitutional and un-American.
غير الدستورية وغير الأمريكية.
And when you put that statement out there
وعندما تطلق هذا التصريح
to a very frothy base
للبسطاء السطحيين
that always is very excited for you to fight Donald Trump,
الذين يظهرون لك الحماسة عندما تحارب ترامب،
and then you have a new one saying, "Wait, these rights are for everybody,
يقول لك أحدهم: (هذه حقوق مكفولة للجميع،
even the president that we don't like."
حتى وإن كان رئيسًا لا يعجبنا)
And that's our job.
وهذه هي مهنتنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: Anthony, you spoke to so many of us so powerfully.
أنتوني، تحدثت إلينا بقوة كبيرة.
Thank you so much. Thank you.
شكرًا جزيلًا لك. (تصفيق)